<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Robert Vitonsky | Software engineering insights</title><description>Tech-savvy&apos;s notes and insights in software engineering: practices, findings, and advice</description><link>https://vitonsky.net/</link><item><title>Languages stats with ISO codes, speakers count, countries list and its population</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/07/15/langstats/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/07/15/langstats/</guid><description>When I work on multi-lingual projects, it always takes a lot of time to estimate and prioritize the localization process. Even if you use machine translation, you can&apos;t just translate all languages in the world, since it takes a long time, and LLM will spend all your money on garbage generations like chars &quot;aa&quot; repeated thousands of times in a row. I built the NPM package 

langstats

 to solve this problem.</description><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 13:42:00 GMT</pubDate><category>project</category><category>opensource</category><category>npm</category><category>announce</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/top-languages.CKhkSzAT.png" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Open source product is a marketing tool</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/06/24/open-source/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/06/24/open-source/</guid><description>Big tech companies invest a lot of effort to sell us the point that every 

good programmer

 must have their own open source project. Many programmers have open source side projects, but quite few of them can explain why they waste their time on it. As a result, they work for free, to make big tech rich. Actually, open source can&apos;t make money for programmers, but may be useful as a promotion tool for them.</description><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 21:50:00 GMT</pubDate><category>opensource</category><category>marketing</category><category>management</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/slc-punk.BnlcSNxT.png" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Don&apos;t Guess My Language</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/05/17/language-detection/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/05/17/language-detection/</guid><description>If you’re still using IP geolocation to decide what language to show, stop screwing around. It’s a broken assumption dressed up as a feature.</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 14:55:00 GMT</pubDate><category>ux-tips</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/the-dreamers-2003.DK9vJg4z.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Hide zeros for users</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/05/15/zeros-in-ux/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2025/05/15/zeros-in-ux/</guid><description>User interfaces everywhere are a bit too generic nowadays, as they must be efficient in terms of maintenance and release time. However, that is not a reason to create a pointless and bad UX. It&apos;s enough to monitor the meaningfulness of interfaces and ask yourself, &quot;Does it make sense?&quot; to make the user experience great.</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 01:07:00 GMT</pubDate><category>frontend</category><category>ui</category><category>ux-tips</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/elevator-panel.TYaAW2vp.jpeg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Build Systems, Not Heroes</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/10/11/system-approach/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/10/11/system-approach/</guid><description>Enterprise programming is the management of system complexity. The main goals of most enterprise projects are to minimize bugs, ensure scalability, and release as soon as possible. These goals are unreachable in projects where people rely on individual skills rather than on a system-based approach.</description><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 13:21:00 GMT</pubDate><category>management</category><category>code quality</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/There%20Will%20Be%20Blood.CYKp_sws.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Software with politic opinion is a security threat</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/06/20/politics-in-software/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/06/20/politics-in-software/</guid><description>The software that has a political opinion implies a bias and high risk for security. Avoid software with a &quot;position&quot; today, so you don&apos;t get hacked tomorrow.</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 18:20:00 GMT</pubDate><category>software</category><category>security</category><category>privacy</category><category>opinion</category><category>facts</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/dr-strangelove.6eqolr6K.png" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Keep the logs for retrospective analysis</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/05/02/retrospective-of-development-logs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/05/02/retrospective-of-development-logs/</guid><description>Development logs are an important part of any project because they allow us to track progress, detect problems, and investigate incidents. Remember the value and advantages of development logs, and preserve as many logs as possible.</description><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 11:40:00 GMT</pubDate><category>management</category><category>code quality</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/Better%20call%20Saul%20-%20Gustavo%20Fring.B_VyTZLA.png" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Decision logs</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/03/20/decision-logs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2024/03/20/decision-logs/</guid><description>Let&apos;s say you need to choose some technology for your project, or you already have problems with some technologies, so you want to replace them with others. If you do not maintain a decision log, you have a high risk of making bad decisions that are biased, based on authority, and take too long.</description><pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 18:20:00 GMT</pubDate><category>management</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/gangs%20of%20new%20york.Cq7NSaH0.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Refusing TypeScript is a signal that you don&apos;t care about code quality</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/09/08/typescript-and-code-quality/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/09/08/typescript-and-code-quality/</guid><description>A few days ago, David Heinemeier Hansson 

announced

 that Turbo 8 

is dropping TypeScript

. I&apos;m okay with that because I don&apos;t even know what Turbo 8 is. However, over the past few years, some frontend programmers have tried to sell me the idea that &quot;TypeScript is useless, just use tests&quot;. I think people with such opinions either don&apos;t care about code quality or simply don&apos;t know what TypeScript is. Here, I will explain why you should use TypeScript.</description><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 18:55:00 GMT</pubDate><category>code quality</category><category>frontend</category><category>software design</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/Anakin-Skywalker.CmQLjsf7.png" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Browser extensions spy on you, even if its developers don&apos;t</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/09/01/malware-in-browser-extensions/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/09/01/malware-in-browser-extensions/</guid><description>I&apos;ve developed a few browser extensions, and every week I receive numerous emails with &quot;revenue offer&quot;. Some experienced developers know that offers like these will inject malware into the browsers of your users, but scammers who make these offers will not tell you about it. They offer &quot;integrations&quot; that don&apos;t look so suspicious. Imagine how many developers have accepted these offers. Then look at the number of extensions in your browser and think about how much risk there is that you have an extension with malware.</description><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 18:25:00 GMT</pubDate><category>security</category><category>cybersecurity</category><category>privacy</category><category>malware</category><category>browser extensions</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/snatch-the-movie.pbpBUZ_-.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>BEM methodology is not about CSS</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/08/16/bem-is-not-about-css/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/08/16/bem-is-not-about-css/</guid><description>Some developers are sure that BEM is just a way to make class names in CSS are unique and, since a modern tools allow to make names unique automatically they have no reasons to use BEM. This is a mistake with a bad consequences, BEM is are methodology about atomic code design, it gives you a standards and guides how to simplify code maintaining.</description><pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 14:28:00 GMT</pubDate><category>frontend</category><category>bem</category><category>architecture</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/the-pusher-movie.C3J2jaLj.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Linguist, an ultimate browser extension for translation</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/07/13/linguist/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/07/13/linguist/</guid><description>The web browser is the most used program for me and for most users of the internet, so it is important for the browser to work efficiently during daily use. Although most browsers have embedded translation features and there are many browser extensions providing translation capabilities, I have found them to be not good enough and unacceptable for intensive use. This is why I have created Linguist - the ultimate browser extension for translation.</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 00:19:00 GMT</pubDate><category>opensource</category><category>project</category><category>promotion</category><category>announce</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/translationOfSelectedText.DNRHQexQ.png" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Design system guide</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/03/18/design-system-guide/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/03/18/design-system-guide/</guid><description>If your project don&apos;t have a design system it is probably usual problem for you, when even a small changes like changes a color for action buttons takes off a lot of time, generate a lot of changes and make user interface look inconsistent. To solve the problems, you should start use a design system. Let&apos;s talk what is it and how to use.</description><pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2023 19:48:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/a_city_by_fmacmanus.yWZQnCH1.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Write detailed description for each pull request</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/01/14/pull-request-description/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2023/01/14/pull-request-description/</guid><description>How often you start code review and can&apos;t understand how this changes fix the problem and even don&apos;t understand is reliable this changes or not? If it periodically happens, you should start write detailed description for each pull request.</description><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 12:40:00 GMT</pubDate><category>code quality</category><category>management</category><category>opensource</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/the-room-2003-tommy-wiseau.-SiNqxhv.png" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Fundamental delusion about interface purposes</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/12/03/interface-expressiveness/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/12/03/interface-expressiveness/</guid><description>We strive to ensure code quality with tests, static code typing, code analyzing, code review and documentation, but some of most popular programming languages like Typescript and Java kill interfaces as concept to describe contract of code.</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 23:35:00 GMT</pubDate><category>architecture</category><category>code quality</category><category>typescript</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/Apple_Magic_Mouse.DcK3Tjf9.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Skeptical thinking</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/06/25/skeptical-thinking/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/06/25/skeptical-thinking/</guid><description>To make good code and think sensibly, you have to practice and improve your skills always. To improve skills, you have to explore the world, meet with exists ideas and be ready to admit that your approach been wrong.</description><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 04:26:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/odb.DElWnLhP.jpeg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>Complicated software is required to evolution</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/06/08/complicated-software/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/06/08/complicated-software/</guid><description>Last time i often hear point about &quot;modern software is unjustified complicated compared to software of 20-30 years ago, modern development approach is wrong and we must focus on performance and energy efficient&quot; and i completely against of this point. Complicated software is move us to the future.</description><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:20:00 GMT</pubDate><category>software</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/matrix-architect.CbkI9vJg.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>The most big problem of UI kits</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/05/23/ui-kit-design/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/05/23/ui-kit-design/</guid><description>UI kits are became popular and today exists really many UI libraries, but almost whole its a have one fundamental architecture problem which make this libraries not much good for wide use. The problem is a not modular design.</description><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 02:30:00 GMT</pubDate><category>frontend</category><category>architecture</category><category>UI kit</category><enclosure url="https://vitonsky.net/_astro/lego.IM53FZrM.jpg" length="0" type="image"/></item><item><title>First post</title><link>https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/05/22/first-post/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://vitonsky.net/blog/2022/05/22/first-post/</guid><description>Welcome to my blog. I&apos;ve create it to expressing my opinion, primarily about programming.</description><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 02:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>